Alright, okay, בוקר טוב.
Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ק"מ, kuf-mem, 140, and we are
in the penultimate פרק. perek. We are in the finally a new
פרק, perek, מי שמת, Mi Shemeit, which deals with initially the issue
here of leaving over an estate, boys and girls, men and women
who are the heirs and well it actually has to be girls
in this context because the הלכה halakha is that the males inherit
and the females if they are under the age of בגרות, bagrut,
maturity, we might sort of say 20, 18, whatever we would say,
for the גמרא Gemara that was 12 and a half, okay, then
they are supported by the estate until they either get married or
until they hit בגרות, bagrut, until they hit that age of maturity.
And the משנה mishna has said that okay so and that means
the best way to think about this conceptually it's like that they
have a lien on, like a debt is owed to them from
the estate, it's an obligation that the estate has to them. So
therefore, if it's נכסים מועטים, nechasim muatim, the important concept here is
נכסים מרובים nechasim merubim or נכסים מועטים. nechasim muatim. If it's נכסים
מרובים, nechasim merubim, I guess we'll start with that, an estate with
a lot of assets, then it means that the girls get supported
and the males get their inheritance and basically what we ended with
yesterday is the definition of מרובים merubim means one penny more than
or a סלע sela whatever than the amount needed to support those
girls until they hit the age of בגרות. bagrut. So if there're
five girls of all different ages and you do the math and
there are
20 girl-years still until they hit בגרות bagrut and it costs a
thousand dollars a year to support somebody in terms of the food
and the clothing or whatever then that's 20,000 dollars for all those
girls until they each individually hit בגרות. bagrut. And you put aside
20,000 dollars and anything more than that is נכסים מרובים nechasim merubim
because that means that there's at least something left over for the
boys to inherit. Okay, so in that scenario the boys inherit something,
whatever exceeds the amount of the support, and the girls get supported.
And if there's less than that then only the girls get supported
and the boys inherit nothing. Okay, so that's the basic framing of
the משנה. mishna. So let's take a look at what the גמרא
Gemara now does with this. So the גמרא Gemara now picks up
on ק"מ kuf-mem and three lines from the top. פשיטא Pshita says
the גמרא, Gemara, it's obvious, מרובים ונתמעטו. merubim venis'mat'u. If they started
with a lot, okay, using my scenario, but let's not make it
just that the boys get a dollar, let's make it I don't
know let's make it that there was 25,000 dollars. 20,000 is put
aside for the girls and 5,000 now is set aside for the
boys. And then the property became worth less. How did the property
become worth less? So, two scenarios, let's say that it was basically
because I don't know that was the money that was in the
stocks. And then all of a sudden the value of the stock
plummeted right after the death and now what had been 25,000 dollars
is only worth 10,000. Okay, another interesting scenario that the רשב"ם Rashbam
describes is let's say it's not really that the property is worth
less but let's say the price of food has shot up. Okay,
so it used to be that it only took 20,000 we thought
when we initially did the assessment it was only going to take
20,000 dollars to support these girls until they got to the age
of maturity. Now with the new price of food it's going to
take 40,000. Okay, but either way you look at it, okay, now
because of either the rising prices of food or because the value
of the stock has plummeted at this stage you need all the
money to go to support the girls. So when the guy died
the boys were going to get 5,000 dollars and the 20,000 was
set aside for the girls. Now a month later all of the
money is needed to support the girls, okay? Got it? Because either
the actual value of the estate has gone down or the price
of food has gone up or whatever it is and you need
all the money to support the girls. What is the story? Do
the boys still get their 5,000 dollars? That's the question, okay? So
it says כבר זכו בהן יורשין. kvar zachu bahen yorshin. Yeah, the
יורשים, yorshim, the heirs, the boys still get their 5,000 dollars and
if it's going to cost more now to support the girls, okay,
so whatever you use that 20,000 dollars you set aside to support
them and if it's not going to buy enough food for them
before they hit בגרות bagrut they're going to not have enough money,
alright, that's going to be tough luck and they're going to have
to go asking for charity or something. Okay, or if the value
of the stocks went down and what had been worth 25,000 dollars
now is I don't know let's say it's half, 12,500.
So then the way at least the רשב"ם Rashbam says it is,
now that's an interesting question. What do you say? Do the boys
have 5,000 still that's like protected totally and the girls have 7,500
or more logically because if you view it like that they've got
property, right, logically that should be like shared equally. So
if this was had been worth 20,000 and that's what you needed
to support the girls and this was worth 5,000 whether it's land
or stocks or whatever and that was what it. The boys inherited.
And then there was a big dip in the market, right? And
now this is worth 10,000
and this is worth 2,500, right? So in that type of a
case basically you would say okay so it's like it's not like
now the boys still have 5,000. If the value of the property
went down why should they be protected
from the fact that the stocks that were assigned to them has
gone down or the real estate that was assigned to them? So
in that case everybody loses proportionally. Okay, but still you don't say
no they get now the girls get this because they still need
20,000 dollars to be supported. So in the case where everything went
down everybody loses out proportionally, okay, and it's not like they still
have a right to be supported and you're going to assign all
the money to them. In the case where the cost of food
has gone up that would be different. Let's say this was the
division and it was cost 20,000 and now it's going to cost
40,000 dollars
to support them okay because the cost of food has doubled. Okay,
in that
case they've got their 5,000 dollars. That's what their inheritance was and
the girls have 20,000 dollars now to support them and the cost
of food has gone up okay sorry what are we going to
do? Okay, now this one makes sense. This one is basically he
died we set aside this money for you that was you getting
your money for your food this was their inheritance and now we
can't help it if value of food starts changing. What?
I understand but I'm saying like you understand the logic for that.
However in the other case alright Mickey let me just finish in
the other case where the value of stuff has gone down right
so like and now this is worth this like you might be
inclined to say one minute if conceptually we think of it as
as they have a lien on the estate to be supported right
so in this case when the value has gone down okay but
then they've only they haven't collected their full value why don't they
keep on taking money from the estate the estate owes them to
be supported so there's two ways of thinking about this. One is
that it's like their debt has already been paid off. This money
has already been assigned to them so now that property values have
changed your debt has already been paid off okay and the other
is but then the question is and the missing point of this
גמרא Gemara is when did these changes happen? Did בית דין Beis
Din already come or the brothers already come and say let's take
this money and put it in a bank account for you? If
they said that then you understand then like okay then or let's
take these stocks assign them over in your name take this piece
of land signed it over in your name then you understand that
the debt was paid off and what happens
afterwards happens afterwards what are you going to do? Okay, but if
the father just died and nobody's done anything yet and two days
later the value of the stock has dropped why has the debt
been paid off? They owe the money let them keep on taking
the money from the estate until their debt has been paid off.
So right I understand you could say it in both cases but
in this one it's clearer. So and it sounds like we're talking
even in that case when nothing has been given to them they
just the father just died logically this would be the division two
days later the value went down all right but if they're real
creditors then they need to be keep on getting paid until the
debt is paid off. So it sounds like and sort of תוספות
Tosafot makes this point
that we want in this case to protect the brothers and the
reason we want to protect the brothers is I mean because we
want there to be some נחלה דאורייתא Nachala DeOraisa right we want
there to be some real inheritance. It is not ideal if all
of the money goes to support the girls I mean we'll do
it if we've got to do it because that's the girls need
the support and they're not seen in that society as being able
to earn money for themselves or whatever they need to be protected
but so obviously that's what's going to happen if it's a small
estate they get supported but it's not great because that means there's
no real inheritance of the תורה Torah okay so therefore in a
case like this even if none of the money has yet been
given to them it's just that when he died it would have
worked out this way and now the values have dropped and now
they're not going to get enough money to support themselves in that
case we're going to say since it's the moment of death we
would have given them 5,000 dollars they're going to keep that 5,000
dollars okay or this piece of land or whatever the proportional amount
is.
Wait even everything in
when
the division was two days later? No the גמרא Gemara is not
מחלק Mechalek so it doesn't matter even if the property wasn't physically
given to them. If it was put in their bank account the
debt was paid off it all makes sense but the גמרא Gemara
can say it could have happened the minute after the father died
that the property values changed and the brother or the cost of
food changed or whatever it was and the brothers already got their
inheritance. Why? If they were real creditors then until the debt is
paid the debt isn't paid. So it seems to be no we're
just protecting the interest not the interest because that's said wrong the
interest we should care about the girls they're not going to be
able to earn money for themselves we need to protect their interest
but we're protecting sort of the religious importance of there being a
נחלה דאורייתא Nachala DeOraisa right. At the expense of the girls. At
the expense of the girls. So in the case where when the
father died, there was a big enough estate for them to get
something, then even though it hadn't been divided yet, things have changed
now, they're still going to get something. Yes, Charlie.
Does it work the other direction too?
Well that's what we're about to get to. What happens if it's
the other direction? Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says that's פשיטא, peshita,
certainly not פשיטא peshita to me, but for the גמרא Gemara that's
פשיטא. peshita. פשיטא מרובין ונתמעטו כבר זכו בהם יורשים. Peshita merubin venismatu
kvar zachu bahem yorshim. They already got a piece of the estate
and you know maybe they'll lose proportionally depends on what the scenario
was, but we're not going to take away a piece of the
estate that should have been coming to them if at the moment
of death it was a big estate.
Okay? Now, מועטין ונתרבו מאי? muatim venisrabu mai? How about if it
was the opposite? Okay? The estate, again, it's going to cost twenty
thousand to support them, the estate here was only worth, you know,
fifteen thousand dollars,
so they weren't even going to have enough money to fully support
the girls, okay, and then a day after the father died, the
values of the stock, the values of the property, whatever, shot up,
and now this is now worth twenty-five thousand.
Okay, what would you say here? Would you say the girls have
gotten the entire estate, because at the moment of death, the entire
estate was enough or not even enough, but you know, to support
them, so that was totally awarded to the girls, okay, and now
the value has gone up, so now they'll just keep it? Or
do you say, no, you know, since at the end of the
day they only are getting it to support themselves, we will, if
there's anything extra as it were, we're going to award that now
to the boys. Alright? So and based on what I've already told
you, this idea that תוספות Tosafot introduces, not explicit in the גמרא,
Gemara, that we want to protect the idea of נחלה דאורייתא, nachala
d'Oraita, it's pretty clear how we would look at it. Okay? And
that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
Well the problem with that is, and you know then two days
later it can go back down to what it was.
Right, and that is a question, do you keep on changing it?
Okay, exactly. And also in this case, like, would we say this,
it's one thing to say this if we haven't yet put the
money in their bank account. If you haven't put the money in
the bank account, then this is obvious. If you treat them as
creditors, if they are the estate owes them twenty thousand dollars, and
when the father died it's worth fifteen thousand, and he hasn't yet
taken payment of it or whatever, okay, and then the value went
up and now it's worth twenty-five thousand, so of course he doesn't
take the whole twenty-five thousand, he takes the amount of his debt.
Okay? So clearly if you look at them as creditors and they
haven't gone into their bank account, that would be true. Okay, the
interesting question is, and this will be a debate of רשבם Rashbam
and תוספות, Tosafot, what if it already was put in their bank
account? Okay? And let's make it easier, let's say it's twenty thousand.
So if you look at them as creditors and it was already
put in their bank account, you would say the debt has been
paid off and now it's their property value that has gone up.
Okay? But let's take a look at what, but you know, you
would have said that before as well. Okay? So let's take a
look at what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay. פשיטא מרובין ונתמעטו כבר
זכו בהם יורשים. Peshita merubin venismatu kvar zachu bahem yorshim. מועטין ונתרבו
מאי? Muatim venisrabu mai? ברשות יורשים קיימי? Birshut yorshim kaime? Is it
in the under,
even when they're going to get paid for their support, fundamentally we
look at the property as still being under the control of the
sons, which makes sense. You look at them as creditors and you
look at the estate as being inherited by the sons. So if
they're basically creditors and the estate is inherited by the sons, so
then fine, the values went up but they don't get the extra,
the increase, they just are able to collect the amount owed to
them. Okay. הילכך ברשות יורשים שבח? Hilkach birshut yorshim shvach?
Therefore, in the under control of the heirs it the value went
up and and the girls only get their support. או דילמא, O
dilma, or do you say, סילוקי מסלקי יורשים מהכא? siluki mesalki yorshim
mehacha? They were loosed from here. Once at the time of death
it was not it was a case of מועטין, muatim, we looked
at the value of the estate and we said there's only enough
or not even enough to support the girls, then we're basically saying
we don't look at it at that moment as the boys inherited
and the girls have a lien. In that we would just say
the boys there was nothing for the boys to inherit. It all
went to the girls. And if it all went to the girls,
then the value went up under the girls' you know while it
was under the girls' ownership and they they get the benefit.
Okay. Yeah it goes up and down again.
I know. So no, the גמרא's Gemara not going to have that,
but that is an excellent question. You're right, I mean once we're
reassessing, we should constantly be reassessing. Okay. Absolutely. And then that really
puts the girls in a bad position, which just basically means, like
you know, they're always they're never going to get more than their
support, which makes sense. Okay. But are they ever but they could
always stand to get less even if there was enough money initially
and so on, yeah.
So is that is that how it works in terms of determining
what they like calculated you know there's five years until she's probably
going to get married, this is what she...
Well until she's a בוגרת, bogeret, right? Okay. Yeah.
And then and
I mean if she she got married earlier, she would stop being
supported, but that's you don't have a finite way to deter, you
don't have a knowledge when she'll get married, so what you would
use was the maximum. maximum possible support would be until she was
a בוגרת. bogeret.
And do you factor in like increased costs? I don't, I guess
I was...
Oh, increased costs of food or whatever? Through time?
That means like each year she gets an allowance? Right. I'm imagining
it in one way, which seems
a lot harder than the other. Yeah, that's an excellent question. Well,
I imagine in terms of figuring out the amount, you would, you
would try to estimate, like, you know, as their, you know, food
bills would go up as they would start getting older, whatever. I
mean, I assume you would figure that in in terms of estimating
the costs. But the question about how the funds would be distributed
is
an excellent question and it goes back to how we think about
this. Do we put all the money into a bank account for
them and have some אפוטרופוס apotropus because remember they're all minors, right?
Have some אפוטרופוס apotropus basically control the funds and determine how to
dole it out, right? Or is all the money held by the,
by the sons, and, you know, and then they have to come
when they need more money? Okay, so it's going to seem תוספות
Tosafot is going to talk about a moment in time when it's
when they, when they were גובה goveh it. When it, so it
does actually seem, it doesn't happen automatically, but it does actually seem
that yes, they would come and demand it from the estate and
the money would be taken and put aside for them. Okay, and
then presumably some אפוטרופוס apotropus would control its distribution.
And if something happened like there was a famine and the cost
of food went up?
Right, tough luck for them. That's exactly what we're talking about. Right,
even though the result will be, will be that they won't be
supported, or the value that was stocks, they assigned some stocks in
their name and then the value of the stocks went down or
land, that's what it basically says. It's going to be like tough
luck for them, you know?
So and now we're seeing that if the value goes up, right,
that they might have to give the increase of the value over
the amount needed to support them back to the brothers. So it's
basically like they're never going to get more than their support and
if the value goes down, they're not going to be able to
make up the difference, right? So it's like the worst of both
worlds. So the גמרא Gemara says, although we haven't given that answer
to that case yet, תא שמע ta shema come and hear. דאמר
רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן de'amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan יתומים
שקדמו ומכרו בנכסים מועטים yetomim shekadmu umachru benechasim muatim מה שמכרו מכרו.
mah shemachru machru.
If the heirs went and in the case of נכסים מועטים nechasim
muatim it was only twenty thousand dollars or less and here the,
so here these are the girls and they're getting, you know, they're
getting all of this because it's going to take twenty thousand dollars
to support them, okay? And comes along these guys, the sons who
basically tell those guys tough luck and they sold it all off
to somebody, okay? The הלכה halacha is that it's a good sale.
Now, it's a good sale and the money still might have to
go to the girls, okay? But the girls can't object and say
you had no right to sell it. And if they were stupid
and sold it for too little, right, it's tough luck on the
girl, meaning, so it's not like they really get anything from having
made that sale, that's not our point right now. The point is
though the sale was valid. Which means whose property is this really?
It's really theirs. Their property that the girls have a lien on.
Okay, so since it's their property because they can sell it and
the girls have a lien, then that means that if the property
value went up, the girls aren't going to get now it's twenty-five
thousand dollars,
they have a twenty thousand dollar debt against this property which is
inherited by the sons, it makes sense that that's what's happening here.
The sons are the heirs, the estate owes money to the girls,
okay? And therefore the sons can sell it. If now that's worth
a lot more money, the girls are not going to get more
than the debt, than the twenty thousand. But the irony though is
that if the property goes down, right, if it was worth forty
thousand and now it's worth twenty, if it really is just a
debt they should still get their full twenty, right? That was the
first case. And then we say no, no, no, once they got
a piece of the estate, that's being
protected.
What should they do but to immediately sell for twenty thousand dollars
so that the daughters don't have this concern anymore? You mean of
the value of the property?
Of the value of the property changing, right. Change it into cash
and then put that cash away, right, exactly. Well you could, the
גמרא Gemara isn't giving business advice, the גמרא Gemara is just talking
about הלכה. halacha. Now I should say, wait, I want to say
one thing. There's an important מחלוקת machloket between תוספות Tosafot and the
רשב"ם Rashbam about till when can the boy sell it. Let's say
the girls come to the court and they say, okay, we want
to do an assessment of the value of the property about what's
going to take to support us and we want that money that
put aside for us. And בית דין Beit Din comes along and
they say okay, fine, the whole estate is worth whatever it is,
twenty thousand dollars, it's exactly the value that's going to cost, this
property is yours, we're awarding this property to you, okay? And בית
דין Beit Din was גובה goveh the property for the girls. According
to the רשב"ם Rashbam then it's too late for the boys to
sell it, which makes sense.
And if it went
down then the boys wouldn't get it? Whatever, yeah, exactly, exactly, then
it's totally the girls', they get the increase of value, whatever, makes
total sense. תוספות Tosafot says even after that moment, even after that
point, it's still under the boys' control, which basically means that... You
know, and this gets I think somewhat to Jenna's question, they're not
like a standard creditor. A standard creditor is you owe me twenty
thousand dollars, give me the money, I take the money, I walk
away. Here, it's a concept of ongoing support, right? So it's really
not like they're coming with a twenty thousand dollar debt. It's really
like the estate has an obligation to continue to support them until
a certain time. So it's like today, the estate owes them two
dollars. Tomorrow, it'll owe them two dollars again, and another two dollars
again every single day, right, it has to support them. So in
that way, even if the property was set aside, it was more
like, it was more like set aside for them to ensure that
they would get support from it, but it was never given to
them. And therefore, in that case, the boys—it's always really still owned
by the sons, and the sons could always still sell it. So
that's like an important conceptual question: Is there ever a moment where
the girls really take full possession of that full amount? And according
to the רשב"ם, Rashbam, the answer is yes, and according to תוספות,
Tosafot, the answer is no. So if you want to look at
the first line in תוספות, Tosafot, he says יתומים שקדמו ומכרו, Yetomim
shekadmu umachru, he says פירש בקונטרס, Peirush bekuntres, שקדמו ומכרו קודם שעמדו
בדין לגבות לבנות נכסים מועטים. shekadmu umachru kodem she'amdu b'din lighbot libnot
nechasim muatim.
Okay,
before there was a court case and it was awarded to the
girls, that's when the boys can sell it. ומיהו ל"ר נראה דאפילו
כבר תפסו הבנות, Umihu le'Ri nira d'afillu kvar tafsu habanot, even if
they seized the property, או הגבו להם בית דין, o higbu lahem
beit din, אם מכרו האחים מכרו. im machru ha'achim machru. ואף על
פי שהגבו להם בית
דין יפה,
Ve'af al pi shehigbu lahem
beit
din yafe, הגבו
להם, higbu lahem,
because conceptually you don't see it as the בית דין Beit Din
is now saying here this is yours. What they're doing is, here
this is the property of the estate that is set aside to
support you. But the support is an ongoing support, it's not like
one big debt that's paid at that moment, right? Which makes total
sense. Yes. All right.
So the boys sold them but if the girls have a lien
on
the buyer?
No, because the girls only have a right to be supported by
the estate with the money that's actually... מזון האישה והבנות Mezon ha'isha
vehabanot is only... it's only, I think it doesn't apply to לקוחות
lakuchot because we sort of discussed that yesterday when we're talking about
support of the
widow because what do you call it? Because
it's not fair for a buyer that he should have a lien
where the amount of the lien fluctuates and is not clear what
it is. So that's a good point. But yes, the girls only
have a right to collect from the estate while it's under the
control of the boys. Okay? So if it gets sold, they don't
have liens on the property because we have to protect the buyers
because this is an indeterminate amount about how much it's going to
require to support them. Okay, but the money that the boys would
get, that still could go to support them. Okay, it's not only
property that... real estate they have a right to. Okay, let's keep
on going. Okay. יתיב רבי ירמיה קמיה דרבי אבהו. Yativ Rabbi Yirmiya
kamei d'Rabbi Abbahu. Rabbi Yirmiya was sitting in front of Rabbi Abbahu,
ובעא מיניה, uva'a minei, asked him: אלמנה מהו שתמעיט בנכסים? Almana mahu
shetam'it benechasim?
How about, so this is getting to a similar scenario
as David, how about the guy dies and not only are there
the boys and the girls, okay, but there's also a widow? Now,
let's say this case, that there was some money here for the
estate, for the boys to get it
when he died, okay,
so there we go. Okay, there was some money, so we thought
that there was going to be enough to support the girls and
something for the boys to inherit. But what we forgot was the
dead person's widow, okay, mother potentially, right, she could be stepmother, okay.
So now she also gets supported from the estate until she gets
married or until they decide to pay her off or she decides
to take a lump sum payment. So we don't know how much
that's going to be. If nobody gives her the lump sum payment,
maybe she's never going to get remarried or whatever. Okay, but let's
for now, even though we don't know the amount, let's for now
estimate it at ten thousand dollars. Okay, so here's the question.
In this case, right, boys get five, girls get ten, שלום, shalom,
wonderful. But is that—so that would be a נכסים מרובים nechasim merubim
scenario. Do we factor in the amount owed to the widow? Well,
I'll tell you in a minute. If we factor in the amount
owed to the widow, then the estate is only worth
fifteen thousand, and then the girls get all of it. If we
don't factor it in, then you do this. Now you should say,
what difference does it make whether you factor it or not factor
it in? Either way,
she's going to come and want her debt to be paid, right?
Yes. Okay.
But does she get it from the sons though?
What? The one who's responsible for... the boys,
right?
Right. So that would be... so that would be... so that would
be an interesting question as well. Meaning if she... in this scenario,
right, if you first... so yeah, I might have even made it
too complicated. But right, the question is, let's say—forget this, let's say
there was not enough for the boys, okay, and they had equal
liens on the estate. Right, so there wouldn't be any preference for
the daughters over the widow. They'd all, they'd all sort of have
to share and in the end they'd all be מפסיד, mafsid, they'd
all sort of lose out. Okay. But the question, but yes, but
that's a good question. So in this case, what difference does it
make if we consider this to be, the question is, do we
consider this to be it was מרובין merubin and then it was
like oh what a surprise the widow comes along and now it's
נתמעטו, nismatu, right, and now it's מרובין merubin that's now shrunk because
now we've realized there's this other debt? Or does it start as
מועטין? muatin? Okay. Now what is the נפקא מינה nafka mina between
those two? So the נפקא מינה nafka mina I have to remind
myself here what the גמרא Gemara said, hold on let me just
make sure I get this right. I think it
was...
yes,
so let's make it an easier case, okay? Let's say it was
fifty thousand like this. So if you say, okay, if you say
that first we sort of assign that before we look at the
size of the estate, the estate was twenty-five thousand, okay,
so in that type of a case, right, the total estate was
twenty-five thousand, we'd say fine, twenty thousand to the girls,
five thousand to the אלמנה, almanah, the boys inherit nothing. That would
be if we were to sort of start by viewing it as
though it redefined the size of the estate. Okay. Let's say however
that we were and in that fine, let's say however
we viewed it as a large, ah if we first viewed it
as a large estate מרובין merubin and then she came along and
wanted her five thousand dollars, where would she take that money from?
So do you remember what the גמרא Gemara said by מרובין ונתמעטו?
merubin ve'nismatu? What does the גמרא Gemara say about
מרובין ונתמעטו? merubin ve'nismatu? כבר זכו בהם יורשין. kvar zachu bahem yorshin.
So in that type of a case if you started by awarding
the boys their five thousand dollars
and then a creditor shows up, okay, it's not clear, maybe she
would take it equally from the two of them, maybe she would
take it all from the girls, but there's a sense in that
case of כבר זכו בהם יורשין. kvar zachu bahem yorshin.
So if you start by saying one minute, here's the estate twenty-five
thousand dollars, twenty thousand to them, five thousand for them, the boys
got nothing. So you'd start by saying the boys got nothing, so
they started with nothing they end with nothing. But if you start
by saying no, they got twenty, they got five, oh wait, here's
the אלמנה, almanah, well then you say כבר זכו בהם היורשים. kvar
zachu bahem hayorshim. So that's what I was saying before. Right. And
in that, in that case, it's not clear, would you say in
that case she takes equally from the two or she splits it
within the girls, but anyway we would think about it differently based
on this principle of כבר זכו בהם יורשין. kvar zachu bahem yorshin.
Factor into the beginning.
I know, logically you totally should. I understand, I understand. I totally
agree with you. It's not a surprise. The guy dies and the
first thing you look at is the widow and the kids.
Right. Also is there a question as to which takes preference, the
חיוב chiyuv of the כתובה ketubah payment or the מזונות mezonot to
the daughters?
That,
right, so that's not clear yet. I think in the end we
say that it's equal, but the גמרא Gemara has not addressed that
yet. Okay. So then if it is equal, then of course you
should look at it all immediately. Right. Exactly.
What if there's absolutely nothing left? Do the heirs have an obligation
to support the widow and the daughters if there's nothing at all?
No, they don't. Okay, it's only a lien on the estate, not
on the people.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Let me just check one more thing in תוספות. Tosafot.
Okay, anyway, so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay, so מי אמרינן כיון דאית לה מזונות ממעטא? mi amrinan keivan
de'it lah mezonot mameita? Since she gets מזונות, mezonot, she reduces, and
you look at it start by נכסים מועטים nechasim muatim and the
boys are out. או דלמא כיון דאילו מינסבא לית לה? o dilma
keivan de'ilu minsava leit lah? One minute, the widow doesn't necessarily always
get מזונות, mezonot, she could always get married and then she would
no longer be entitled to מזונות. mezonot. הכא נמי לית לה. hacha
nami leit lah. So you don't look at, you don't take her
portion off the top. Same with the girls. I know. So תוספות
Tosafot asks this. תוספות Tosafot says it doesn't make any sense. The
same is exactly true about the girls. The widow is in no
different state than the girls. Right. It's a hard גמרא Gemara to
understand. But the גמרא, Gemara, so I don't know the answer, but
let's just work with it. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara is basically
saying since the widow won't necessarily always get support, you should view
her as a stage two and not a stage one, like you
don't factor her in initially. And since you didn't factor her in
initially, you consider it a מרובין merubin and the boys were already
זוכה zocheh to a portion of the estate, and therefore they're not
going to totally lose out, they retain some ownership. that even now
that the widow is introduced at stage two. Okay, so אי תיבעי
לומר כיון דאי מנסבא לית לה מזונות. ei tivay lomar kivan d'ei
minasva leit lah mezonot. Now let's say you say since were she
to get married she wouldn't have מזונות, mezonot, therefore you view her
as a stage two and you assess the estate initially as a
נכסים מרובים nechasim merubim estate, which is going to work to the
benefit of the boys. השתא נמי ליתא, hashta nami leisa, so here
too also you sort of don't factor her in initially. So בת
אשתו מהו שתמעיט בנכסים? bat ishto mahu shetema'it benechasim? Now here's another
thing you probably don't know about yet, which is another person who
gets supported by the estate, a classic thing that they would write,
I mean they don't, it's not always, you'd have to demand it
and get the husband to agree to it, but here a woman
comes and she's getting married and it's a second marriage for her
and she has a daughter from her first marriage and she says
to the guy fine, you want me to marry you? Fine. Here's
what I want you to write in the כתובה ketubah though. I
want you to write in the כתובה ketubah that if you die
that then my daughter here from the first marriage, right, she's not
going to be supported, she's not your kid, I want you to
write in the כתובה ketubah that she's entitled to five years of
support if you die from the estate. Okay, so that would be
a classic thing that would be written in for somebody that would
marry and take on stepkids, specifically stepdaughters.
It's sort of like בני דכרין benei dikhrin but בת דכרין. bat
dikhrin. Right.
Okay, so in that case, okay, do you also factor in so
here's her daughter from a different marriage, okay, and that's
going to be
five thousand dollars, okay, you also factor that in and then to
initially say what the size of the estate was. And again, the
reason it matters is if it's נכסים מרובים nechasim merubim the sons
have a certain amount that's protected, okay, they're going to maintain some
of the estate.
If the wife dies, does she still get the כתובה?
ketubah? From her first husband? Yes, she gets the lump sum payment,
she doesn't get the ongoing support. Yes. Okay, so בת אשתו מהו
שתמעיט בנכסים? bat ishto mahu shetema'it benechasim? מי אמרינן כיון דכי מנסבא
נמי אית לה וממעטה? mi amrinan kivan d'chi minasva nami it lah
umema'atah?
So here's an interesting irony about the stepdaughter. She's protected, she's given
five years of support. On the one hand, that's not until בגרות,
bagrut, might be that she only hits the age of ten. On
the other... the support of the girl, of the stepdaughter. The stepdaughter
the classic would be she'd be supported for five years when the
husband would agree to it.
Regardless of whether she hits בגרות? bagrut?
Regardless of whether she hits בגרות, bagrut, but not regardless of whether
she gets married. If she gets married the support stops, okay, so
it says like this. I'm sorry, no, I take it back. Regardless
of whether she hits בגרות bagrut and regardless of whether she gets
married, excuse me. She's just given a flat five years support, okay.
So therefore because she's going to always get that support five years
whether she hits בגרות bagrut whether she gets married, so it's a
little ironic, right, it's better in a way than a normal daughter.
Or five years or whatever's specified?
It's
whatever's specified, but it seems like there was a standard of five
years, okay. So do we say that therefore she's definitely going to
get five years of support, right, and therefore we should cut you
know take that off the top? מי אמרינן כיון דכי מנסבא
נמי אית לה וממעטה? mi amrinan kivan d'chi minasva nami it lah
umema'atah? Even were she to get married she would still collect her
support and therefore it's more it's a definite debt that the estate
owes and therefore we should take it off the top.
ממעטה מה שיומעיט מהנכסים. mema'atah mah sheyoma'it mahannechasim.
She's ממעיט mema'it the estate and we consider it נכסים מועטים, nechasim
muatim, not רבים ונתמעטו, rabbim venitma'atu, but we start by being מועט.
muat. Right. או דילמא כיון דאי מתה
לית לה. o dilma kivan d'ei metah leit lah. Or do we
say since were she to die she wouldn't get support. ולא ממעטה.
velo mema'atah. It's still not definite that money is coming out of
the estate. I understand. I understand, it's pretty unlikely, it's a young
girl, the likelihood she's going to die. Okay, ואי תיבעי לומר כיון
דאי מתה לית לה ולא ממעטה. ve'ei tivay lomar kivan d'ei metah
leit lah velo mema'atah. Maybe
since were she to die she wouldn't get it, we won't consider
it like we start by taking that money off the top. So
בעל חוב מהו שימעיט? ba'al chov mahu sheyama'it? How about just a
common creditor? Okay, forget these people. סתם, stam, a creditor. The estate
owes this guy this whatever, the estate just owes this guy five
thousand dollars, okay. So do we say that therefore the guy dies,
twenty five thousand dollars, five thousand is owed to creditors, twenty thousand
is needed for the girls, the boys get nothing. End of story.
או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say no, the estate was
worth twenty five thousand, twenty thousand for them, five thousand for them,
comes along a creditor, he's owed five thousand dollars, כבר זכו בהן
היורשים, kevar zachu bahen hayorshim,
okay, and maybe again maybe it's shared equally, but it's not all
taken from the boys. All right, which way do you say it?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. בעל חוב מהו שימעיט
בנכסים? ba'al chov mahu sheyama'it benechasim? מי אמרינן כיון דכי מאיית נמי
אית ליה? mi amrinan kivan d'chi mayet nami it leh? Even if
the בעל חוב ba'al chov dies, in this way the money is
most it's definitely going to have to leave the estate, right, because
as opposed to the stepdaughter whatever, even if the בעל חוב ba'al
chov dies, his heirs can come and collect the money owed. to
him, okay? So that money is always gonna have to get paid
out. Do we say כיון דכי מיית נמי אית ליה, keivan de'chi
mayis nami is leh, he's still entitled even if he's dead, his
heirs are entitled, ממעט, mima'et, so we have to take that money,
you know, and deduct it from the value of the estate? או
דילמא, o dilma, or do you say כיון דמחסר גוביינא, keivan de'mechasser
govayna, ah, but it still hasn't been collected, לא ממעט, lo mima'et,
it doesn't matter, we still don't deduct it from the estate. Okay
now, of course, a lot of this sounds crazy, right? You would
think you would have to factor all this stuff in to determine
how much is left. The fact that we're pushing and saying we
don't is again, this gets back to תוספות Tosafot's point that we
want to try to make sure to try to I wouldn't say
protect the son's interests, but we want to try to make there
be a נחלה דאורייתא. nachala d'oraisa. The effect of all of this
is saying, the effect of saying we don't consider we don't deduct
the value of the estate, we consider it a large estate, and
then we factor in the creditors and the widow and all of
that, so it's מרובין ונמעטו, merubin v'nismatu, the effect that has is
that we get to award some of the property to the sons.
And therefore it doesn't and therefore they're left with some property, so
it has the effect of retaining some degree of
a נחלה דאורייתא. nachala d'oraisa. And I think because I just want
to read one more line in the גמרא Gemara which basically just
does the same thing in reverse. It says like this: איכא
דבעי לה איפכא גיסא, ika d'baei lah ipecha gisa, some start in
the opposite direction. בחוב מהו שימעיט בנכסים? be'chov mahu she'yamit bi'nechasim? Does
a בחוב be'chov ממעיט בנכסים? mima'et bi'nechasim? And even if you say
that a בעל חוב ba'al chov is ממעיט בנכסים, mima'et bi'nechasim,
so בת אשה מהו שתמעיט? bas isha mahu she'tamat? How about the
stepdaughter? Because maybe only the בעל חוב ba'al chov who gets it
even if he's dead. But would the stepdaughter also be ממעיט? mima'et?
And even if you say the stepdaughter מנכסים אלמנה מהו שתמעיט? minechasim
almanah mahu she'tamat? Maybe the stepdaughter gets it because she's gonna get
it whether she gets married or not. But how about the widow?
Would the widow be ממעיט בנכסים? mima'et bi'nechasim? אלמנה, almanah, okay, so
that's sort of so it's the same thing but reverse but it's
a huge difference which way you do it. Because based on the
order you do it, it's suggesting where your פסק psak is gonna
end up. The first way we had it, it sounded like the
גמרא Gemara was keep kept on pushing to the conclusion that they
are not ממעיט mima'et the estate, right? Even a בעל חוב ba'al
chov is not ממעיט. mima'et. Maybe this person isn't, maybe this person,
how about the... maybe even the בעל חוב ba'al chov isn't ממעיט
mima'et the estate. If you go in the opposite direction, then it
means we're pushing for a conclusion to say they are ממעיט. mima'et.
Fine, let's say the בעל חוב ba'al chov is ממעיט. mima'et. How
about the stepdaughter? Fine, maybe the stepdaughter's ממעיט, mima'et, but how about
the widow? So in that way we're, you know, it's a huge
difference which way you frame the question, right? Which way you're sort
of want, you know, sort of trying to direct the conclusion towards.
Is this the same as asking, you've got the אלמנה, almanah, you've
got the stepdaughter, you've got בנות, banos, you've got בנים? banim? Right.
Who's like who gets paid out first?
No.
And no. The גמרא Gemara's gonna get to that next. No, it's
not the same. Meaning, you could sort of say let's just assume
whatever, like let's assume there are no well not no sons right,
but like how do the if it's between the you know, let's
look at the next question, it's not the same. This is just
a question about the idea of do we say כבר זכו בהן
היורשים? kevar zachu bahen hayorshim? When we assess, do we assume that
there's value that they inherit and then they're not gonna totally lose
that? The question about how you pay off all of your different
creditors, right, the estate has all these various creditors and what's the
order and priorities, to some degree that's gonna be the next question.
But people do understand that the way in which we asked the
question just now about the widow and the stepdaughter and the creditor,
right, based on which way you start and which, you know, is
a huge difference about whether you're seeming to push to a conclusion
that it always is ממעיט mima'et in the estate or that it's
never
ממעיט.
mima'et. Yes. Just to make sure that I'm understanding this, this is
assuming there is an estate. If we give it all to the
מלוה, malveh, then no one gets anything.
Right. Exactly. Yeah.
So this issue of not knowing
Well, the creditor might get because then he gets it all to
because he still has liens on it, those liens don't go away.
Yeah, right.
So the issue of not knowing how long like someone's going to
live, right,
have פוסקים posekim
taken into account the development of annuities in modern days?
I'm sure they have, but here we weren't even factoring in their
lifespan. That was the hard thing about the אלמנה almanah is that
how do you factor in anything in terms of the what that's
not clear at all, how would you factor in the אלמנה almanah's
what that would mean, right? I don't know. And the concept of
life? One more.
One more question. Yeah. So if if the father חס ושלום chas
v'shalom before he died gifted everything to his son? Right. So then
the son has no obligation for the מזונות mezonos for the minor
girls after the death?
That's an interesting question. What?
He wouldn't be allowed to like
I mean he can do tricks to get stuff around, but that's
an interesting question because they still have liens on the estate and
we but we've and we've only protected third parties against those liens,
so... That's an interesting question. We don't protect the יורשים yorshim against
liens obviously because that would completely undermine it. So if the יורשים
yorshim have been made
into gift recipients, but
it's would the liens still be valid? Didn't the גמרא Gemara ask
that? Yeah, the גמרא Gemara asked that. The גמרא Gemara said it
asks by א מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat shechiv mera. It says if
a מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera works like a מתנה, matana,
the גמרא Gemara said would it be a נפקא מינא nafka mina
about the אלמנה זו ניזונת? almana zo nizonet? And the גמרא Gemara
says of course אלמנה almana would be ניזונת. nizonet. But that was
a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat shechiv mera. That wasn't that wasn't the
last minute before I
died. So if it was the last minute before I died, it's
not clear what the answer would be. But the גמרא Gemara definitely
said that in the case of the מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv
mera that would not undermine the right, you know, the the אלמנה
almana and the daughters. It's a good question if it was a
case of like a מתנה matana minute before he died. Is that
what was? דף קלח? Daf Kuf Lamed Chet? Hold on.
This again might be a מחלוקת machloket between תוספות Tosafot and רשב"ם
Rashbam that like תוספות Tosafot is saying that the בנים banim all
have it all anyway and they're just giving it out to the
daughters,
but I guess it's their property anyway so it's their property because
the daughter gave it to them so they're still.
Right, although it's still not a personal obligation, it's still very much
is a form of a lien. The question is is the lien
basically a lump sum collectible at once or like, you know, ongoing?
שמשעה שנתנה לו בנכסיו כראוי. Shemesha'a shenatna lo b'nechasav k'ra'uy. No,
that's not that. It's a different גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, I have to
look. It's a good question. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara certainly said
in the case of a מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera that
it would not undermine the widow's right to the estate. What would
be if it was actually a מתנת בריא matnat bari done like
a מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera to take effect a minute
before or something like that? That would be a different story. I
have to find that גמרא. Gemara. All right, but anyway, let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלמנה ובת איזה
מהן קודמת. almana u-bat eizeh mehen kodemet. Let's say you had a
small estate and there wasn't enough money even to support the girls
and there was a widow. Okay, does either one have do they
all get supported equally and when it runs out, it runs out
at the same time for everyone? Or do you prioritize one person's
claim over another? אמר ליה זיל האידנא ותא למחר. Amar leh zil
idana v'ta l'machar. So anyway, so that was that was after all
these questions of is it ממעט mima'et the estate? After all this
question of the creditor and the widow, there was this one final
question of forget ממעט mima'et the estate. If it's competing claims of
the widow and the daughters, does any one of them have precedence?
So he said in all these questions, leave, come back tomorrow. כי
אתא, Ki ata, when he came back tomorrow, אמר ליה פשיטא לי
חדא. Amar leh peshita li chada. I at least have one answer
for you. I don't have an answer for all those questions about
the widow and, you know, the step-daughter and the creditor and whether
it's considered מרובין merubin or מועטין mu'atin or not. That I don't
know. But I have an answer for your last
question. דאמר רבי אבא אמר רבי אסי עשו אלמנה אצל הבת כבת
אצל האחין בנכסים מועטין. D'amar Rabbi Abba amar Rabbi Assi asu almana
etzel habat k'bat etzel ha'achin b'nechasim mu'atin.
They made a widow vis-à-vis the daughter like the daughter vis-à-vis the
sons when there's only a small estate. What does that mean? מה
בת אצל האחין הבת ניזונת והאחין ישאלו על הפתחים. Ma bat etzel
ha'achin habat nizonet v'ha'achin yish'alu al hapetachim. The same way the support
of the daughter comes before the sons, the daughter gets supported and
the sons have to go begging, okay, if it's a small estate.
אף אלמנה אצל הבת האלמנה ניזונת והבת תשאל על הפתחים. Af almana
etzel habat ha'almana nizonet v'habat tish'al al hapetachim.
The widow is supported and the daughters go knocking on the doors.
Now, why do you think she takes precedence? So why you said
it makes sense. Why does it make sense?
Well, I mean first of all, in American law the spouse inherits
right now anyway. Okay. The whole business of children getting anything doesn't
make as much sense, although it does in French law. But I
mean the the daughters are more likely to they're young, they're more
likely to eventually get married. Okay. And an older widow, then she's
less likely to.
Right. So I would say so you could say the daughters are
more likely to be able to get, you know, to young, to
maybe to start getting earning some money, get married off, etc. The
other way to look I agree with Adam and the other way
to look at it is from the perspective of the guy getting
married who's
who's stipulating, who's the one that's obligating himself to his current wife
and to his future daughters. So even though, you know, so the
person he's marrying right now is this woman. So to think that
he sort of prioritized his obligations to this woman over some future
yet unborn daughters, right, makes sense. You could say the opposite. At
the end of the day, you know, a person's daughters kids are
in his own, you know, are his own progeny, his own blood,
you know. The spouse maybe who knows how their marriage goes over
the course of the years. But still, at the time when he's
stipulating at the כתובה ketubah he's got this woman... it makes sort
of sense to think that he's prioritizing his responsibilities to her. So
that's actually what we say in the end, that that comes first.
So mean all these little girls are?
Correct. Okay. Yeah, I mean somebody would have to you'd have to
assign some אפוטרופוס apotropos or something, right? I don't know. What happens
if somebody dies and he has zero money to his estate? Everybody
has to go begging. What are you supposed to do? Okay, עד
כאן. Ad kan. Now אדמון Admon says בשביל שאני זכר הפסדתי? bishvil
she'ani zachar hifsadeti? What, just because I'm a male I'm going to
lose out? Meaning in the case when it's a small estate, the
girls are going to get supported and I'm going to get nothing?
So presumably he's saying like logic at least would dictate—there's a question
we said the other day, yesterday, whether it means that he's actually
arguing as to the הלכה, halacha, but whether he's disagreeing about the
הלכה, halacha, at least logic would dictate that I would also get
supported equally to the daughters. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי קאמר?
mai ka'amar? Now why does he think that just because he's a
man he should have equal rights? Okay, so אמר אביי הכי קאמר.
amar Abaye hachi ka'amar. Here's what he's saying. Okay, listen to this.
בשביל שאני זכר וראוי אני לעסוק בתורה הפסדתי? bishvil she'ani zachar vera'ui
ani la'asok baTorah hifsadeti?
Look,
I'm a male, I'm on a higher spiritual plane than these women.
I could be learning תורה, Torah, so my support should come before
the support of the women. So אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava,
so רבא Rava says אלא מעתה מאן דעסיק בתורה הוא דירית ודלא
עסיק בתורה לא ירית? ela me'ata man de'asik baTorah hu deyaris udela
asik baTorah lo yaris? What,
do you think inheritance is determined based on who's learning תורה? Torah?
So if you've got three sons and one of them is in
ישיבה yeshiva and two of them aren't, maybe only the one who's
learning in ישיבה yeshiva gets the inheritance? It's all very nice to
think that you're more
valuable because of your תורה Torah learning, but since when do we
see that that has legal implications in areas of ירושה? yerusha? That's
a complete non-legal argument. Okay, so אלא אמר רבא הכי קאמר. ela
amar Rava hachi ka'amar. בשביל שאני זכר וראוי אני לירש בנכסים מרובים
הפסדתי? bishvil she'ani zachar vera'ui ani lirash benechasim merubim hifsadeti?
No, my point is—forget that, forget some larger existential claim. I have
a legal privilege. Men in general are privileged within the legal system,
and I will show you that we're privileged within the legal system
in this case too. Because if it's a large estate, I'm going
to get as a son, I'm going to get the actual inheritance
of the estate. You could also have said if there's only boys
and no girls,
but I guess that's the point, if there's boys and girls, the
boys inherit. But they only inherit if it's a large estate. Okay,
so if it's a multi-million dollar estate, the girls will get $10,000
and I the boy will get the whole huge estate. So clearly
I am privileged in this system, and since I'm privileged, I should
get supported even in the case of when it's a small estate.
So הפסדתי בנכסים מועטים? hifsadeti benechasim mu'atim? Should I lose out? Now
the answer could be like yes, maybe it's not a question about
privileged—you're privileged and they're
underprivileged—I mean that is what it is, but maybe what it is,
you have certain rights and they have different rights. You know, you
get a large estate and they have more protected support. Because boys
can go out and it's more easy for them to knock on
doors and to earn a living and whatever. So yeah, it's not
like you're always better, sometimes you really win out because of that
privilege, sometimes you lose. Okay, there are different considerations. I do think
it is interesting the argument of בשביל שאני זכר וראוי לעסוק בתורה.
bishvil she'ani zachar vera'ui la'asok baTorah. It does get a little bit
to the idea about like, you know, look, obviously it's a sensitive
issue, you know, like Rav Moshe Feinstein was once asked about the
fact about, you know, sort of the ברכה bracha of שלא עשני
אשה. shelo asani isha. Does that sort of show that Judaism considers
women to be on a lower
spiritual plane than the men? You know, I mean I'm sure you're
all familiar with the various answers and apologetics and so on. But
sometimes this phrase of ראוי לעסוק בתורה ra'ui la'asok baTorah is used
as a way of indicating that like men are seen as, you
know, existentially higher. One place you have it is a מחלוקת בית
הלל ובית שמאי machlokes Beis Hillel uBeis Shamai about whether the מצוה
mitzvah of פרו ורבו pru urvu is about, you know, about a
boy and a girl or two boys. And בית שמאי Beis Shamai
says it's about two
boys because they're ראוי לעסוק בתורה. ra'ui la'asok baTorah. So it sort
of seems to say—it's very nice, you can't repopulate a world with
all boys. Okay, but nevertheless he doesn't see it—what?
בית שמאי Beis Shamai says a boy
and—no, הלל Hillel says a boy and a girl. בית שמאי Beis
Shamai says two boys. So anyway, all right, so anyway, so it's
interesting seeing that brought in. That wasn't just chance happening to mention
תורה, Torah, it seems to be a pointer to a sort of
larger type of an argument about this.
Okay, so where do we stand?
What's—we've had like 15 different positions, I don't even know what have
we concluded.
Well, no, we don't have a conclusion about the case about whether
it's about these various debts that are owed, whether it's considered מרובים
בנכסים מועטים merubim benechasim mu'atim or just מועטים. mu'atim. We don't have
a conclusion, I don't know how we'd פסק pasken the מעשה. ma'aseh.
Yeah,
so we—oh, that we said yesterday. That the רשב"ם Rashbam says we
rule like אדמון Admon and תוספות Tosafot says we don't rule like
אדמון, Admon, and he brings a lot—he says the fact the גמרא
Gemara basically always ignores אדמון Admon when it discusses the scenarios of
a small estate or
whatever. So תוספות Tosafot thinks that אדמון Admon isn't really arguing, he's
just pointing out the irony.
Okay, let's just—let's read at least the next משנה. mishna. All right,
now look at this, we're falling behind.
הניח בנים ובנות וטומטום. hiniach banim uvanot vetumtum. Okay,
now we're getting into a thing. Okay, a טומטום tumtum is not
a hermaphrodite, that's an אנדרוגינוס androgynous who has both male and female
genitalia. A טומטום, tumtum, the genitalia has either not descended or it's
covered up so you don't know yet. Where the presumption is he
only has one set of genitalia, but it's indeterminate at this stage.
So בזמן שנכסים מרובים bizman shenechasim merubim הזכרים דוחין את הבנות hazcharim
dochin et habanot ואת הבנות הקטנות. veet habanot hakeitanot.
So if it's a large estate, they've inherited many millions of dollars
and the girls get ten thousand dollars, whatever their support, so the
boys say to him, "Oh, we think you're a girl. Go just
get the support with the girls." Now the girls could say, "We
think you're a boy. Go get from the part they inherit." So
the point seems to be
that the question is, is he able to do this? But he
would come with a claim against the entire estate, and the most
that he can say like ממה נפשך mima nafshach is the most
she's entitled to from the estate is what a girl would get.
Right? So, you know, so that's what he winds up. He doesn't
take away from the girls, right? All the girls get their money.
Do the boys effectively lose that little bit?
Oh, they only lose a little bit, right. Okay, so נכסים מועטים,
nechasim muatim, if it's a small estate and he says, "Hey, I'm
entitled to get supported. I don't have to go begging." הנקבה דוחה
אותו אצל זכרים. hanekeiva docha oto etzel zcharim. They say, "No, we
think you're a male and you're not entitled and you can't prove
you're female and you're entitled to get support, so you go begging."
Next, okay, so that's sort of wrapping up to the previous משנה.
mishna. Now, once we're dealing with טומטום, tumtum, we look at another
case. האומר אם תלד אשתי זכר יטול מנה. haomer im teleid ishti
zachar yitol maneh.
If my wife gives birth to a boy, he should take a
hundred... give her a hundred, I'll give a hundred-dollar gift.
He should, he should, the boy should. Thank you. The boy, I'm
giving a gift, set a hundred-dollar bond away for my son. So
ילדה זכר יטול מנה. yalda zachar yitol maneh. That's not a big
חידוש. chiddush. Presumably he did this through a קנין. kinyan. Okay, like
I said to Michael, "Here, you know, give me your handkerchief, I'll
take this handkerchief in exchange, you be קונה koneh on behalf of
my unborn child. If he's a boy, you'll be קונה koneh a
hundred dollars on behalf of my unborn child." Okay, if he said
אם תלד אשתי זכר יטול מנה... אם נקבה מאתיים, im teleid ishti
zachar yitol maneh... im nekeiva masayim, ילדה נקבה תטול מאתיים. yalda nekeiva
titol masayim.
If I say, "And if it's a girl, you be קונה koneh
on behalf of her two hundred dollars," and it was a girl,
so two hundred dollars. Okay, now it's not a big חידוש, chiddush,
the big חידוש chiddush really is is that he's able to be
קונה koneh for a... for an עובר. ubar. You might say he
can't be קונה koneh anything on behalf of an unborn child. The
other thing that the גמרא gemara says, and this is exactly maybe
done as a critique to אדמון admon or whatever, the irony here
is that it seems like I'm happier if I have a girl
than a boy, right? I'm willing to set aside more money. Maybe
I just need to protect the girl more than a boy. Okay,
but anyway, but that's an interesting reading that in juxtaposition with אדמון
admon setting up the scenario that I'm gifting more money to my
unborn daughter than to my unborn son. Okay, now אם זכר מנה
אם נקבה מאתיים. im zachar maneh im nekeiva masayim. Okay, now let's
say I say if it's a boy a hundred, if it's a
girl two hundred. וילדה זכר ונקבה. veyalda zachar unekeiva. And now the
simple read of this is it was twins. זכר נוטל מנה נקבה
נוטלת מאתיים. zachar notel maneh nekeiva noteles masayim. Then both of the
conditions are met and the boy gets a hundred, the girl gets
two hundred. The רשב"ם rashbam disagrees with this read. He thinks that
if I say אם זכר מנה אם נקבה מאתיים, im zachar maneh
im nekeiva masayim, if I'm assuming there only to be one son...
one child and it turned out to be twins and I didn't
expect this, then my condition wasn't met at all and nobody gets
anything. Okay, and he reads the משנה mishna זכר ונקבה zachar unekeiva
meaning if it's a boy or if it's a girl, meaning he
reads the ו vov as an or, which then just makes it
very obvious. If I say if it's a boy let it be
a hundred, if it's a girl let it be two hundred, then
if it's a boy he gets a hundred, if it's a girl
she gets two hundred. Which we had before except before I only
said if it's a boy a hundred and in that case it
was a girl she gets nothing. And I say girl two hundred,
if it was a boy he gets nothing. And here I covered
my bases so whichever it is, that's what they'll get. So it's
an interesting question that if I say if it's a boy X
and a girl Y and it's twins, the פשט pshat of the
משנה mishna is both of the kids get. The רשב"ם rashbam says
I wasn't expecting that and they get nothing. Anyway, but now let's
get to the real punchline at the end of the משנה. mishna.
ילדה טומטום. yalda tumtum. Okay, so I said if it's a boy
X, a girl Y, and it's a טומטום. tumtum. So you might
say, well, let him at least get a hundred, the lesser of
the two, right?
So אינו נוטל, eino notel, he doesn't get anything. Now this is
an opinion that טומטום tumtum is not a ספק, safek, טומטום tumtum
is בריה בפני עצמו. beriya bifnei atzmo. Now that is much more
of a logical position by an androgynous. An androgynous has both, I
can't tell you. A טומטום tumtum has one set of genitalia, it's
just we don't know it yet. Okay, and nevertheless, this is a
position that since that's an unusual configuration of the body, okay, it's
not like it's just we're ignorant, that it makes the person's, you
know, sex in itself a different category. So this is all very
nice, you know, it's actually quite interesting, right, you know, sort of
the very, you know, contemporary thing about that not a sex, not
a binary sort of, you know, gender, that there's, you know, intersex
and other types of things. הלכה halacha actually realizes it and even
in a case where it's not both genitalia, at least according to
this opinion. So in that case neither condition is met and this
child is neither male nor female and doesn't get either. Okay, אם
אמר כל מה שתלד אשתי יטול, im amar kol mah sheteleid ishti
yitol, whatever child whether
as long as the child is healthy, right, whether it's a boy
or a girl let him get a hundred, הרי זה יטול. harei
zeh yitol. Fine, that's also not much of a חידוש. chiddush. ואם
אין שם יורש veim ein sham yoresh אלא הוא יורש את הכל
ela hu yoreish et hakol going back to the earlier issue. If
there's no other kids, then he gets it all because whether it's
a boy or a girl, if he's not competing with any other
siblings, then he's the only heir, then he gets it all. Okay,
so the interesting question is going to be is this טומטום tumtum
a בריה בפני עצמה birya bifnei atzmah like in its own category
of sexual identity, or is it considered to be a ספק? safek?
So we'll pick up with that tomorrow.